<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Demos>
	<demo name="MonteCarlo">
		<Headline> $\Large{\pi}$ BY CHANCE </Headline>
		<Description><![CDATA[
					Have you ever considered that there may be some organization to randomness? 
					Or, that some inherent quality of randomness exists which is systematic and 
					determinable? If not, the whole idea may sound a bit paradoxical and unintuitive, 
					however it turns out that this approach to randomness can be useful in solving 
					certain mathematical problems. The so called Monte Carlo method, invented by Polish 
					mathematician Stanislaw Ulam in 1946, uses this idea as its driving principle. In 
					the experiment above, we will be using a Monte Carlo method to estimate the digits 
					of our favorite transcendental number: $\large{\pi}$!
					<br>
					<br>
					<h4 style="display: inline;">Background</h4>
					<br>
					Before we begin, let's think hard about what it means for something to be a random 
					event. First, by characterizing an event as random, we imply that something about 
					that particular event-- its location, time, color, et cetera-- is unpredictable, 
					meaning there is no coherent pattern in the event's random trait. A classic example 
					of this is a coin toss$^{1}$.
					<br>
					 Now, we must ask: "what about the coin toss makes it random?" In this example, it 
					is obvious that we mean that the randomly determined outcome is whether the coin is 
					Heads or Tails. But, we could have instead tossed a standard six-sided die to yield 
					six possible random outcomes. In this way, we have established that we may bound our 
					random variable within a certain range, e.g. two sides of a coin, six sides of a die, 
					within the first cartesian quadrant, within the Republic of Kiribati, et cetera.
					<br>
					Finally, we need to think about what will happen when a random event happens in a 
					sequence. For example, say we toss a coin in succession and tally the number of 
					heads and the total number of tosses.
					<br>
					<br>
					<img src="./experiments/coins.png" width="476" height="84" style="	display: block; margin-left: auto;margin-right: auto;">
					<br>
					<br>
					Here we've tossed the coin five times and can see that we've landed on heads 
					twice. So 2 out of the 5 tosses we have landed on heads;  $\frac{2}{5}$ is $0.4$. But, if 
					we are dealing with a fair coin we would expect that the probability of landing 
					on heads to be $50\%$, or $0.5$, i.e. the coin lands on heads half of the time. Then 
					why are we getting a value of $0.4$? Obviously, 5 is not even and the number of 
					coin tosses cannot be fractional, so we cannot get $0.5$. However, say we decide 
					to try our luck and give the coin one more toss. If it lands on heads that makes 
					3 heads and 3 tails, so the universe makes sense and life is good because we have 
					the exact outcome as our expected outcome according to probability. But say the 
					coin lands on tails. Don't worry, the universe can still make sense, remember we 
					are working with probability! Consider the circumstance in which you toss the coin 
					a large number of times, say an infinite amount of times!   What would happen? Of 
					course, this is impossible in reality, but theoretically as the number of tosses 
					approaches infinity the number of heads divided by the total amount of tosses will 
					equal exactly the expected value: $0.5$! This is explained by the so called Law of 
					Large Numbers. So, the main point we must draw from this is that if we perform a 
					large amount of random experiments in succession we are able to estimate expected 
					probabilities.
					<br>
					<br>
					<h4 style="display: inline;">How Does This Work?</h4>
					<br>
					So keeping in mind our discussion about randomness and probability, let's shift 
					gears and talk about $\large{\pi}$. We know $\large{\pi}$ is the ratio of any circle's circumference to 
					it's diameter and that it is irrational, i.e. it cannot be represented by a simple 
					fraction and it has an infinite amount of digits to the right of the decimal point. 
					So does anyone actually know the value of $\large{\pi}$? No, we only know around five trillion 
					of it's digits and, since it goes on forever, we will never know its true value. But 
					we can estimate its value which is what we're here to do.
					<br>
					<br>
					Let's begin by introducing a circle with radius $r$ and a square with each side equal to $2r$.
					<br>
					<br>
					<img src="./experiments/circle.png" width="200" height="200" style="display: inline-block; left: 130px; position: relative;">
					<img src="./experiments/square.png" width="200" height="200" style="display: inline-block; left: 260px; position: relative;">
					<br>
					<br>
					Now, let's write out the the equations determining their respective areas.
					<br>
					\begin{equation}
						A_{\small{\bigcirc}} = \pi r^{2}
					\end{equation}
					\begin{equation}
						A_{\Box} = (2r)^{2}
					\end{equation}
					Of course, we don't know the value of $\large{\pi}$, so is there any other way we can 
					represent the area of the circle? Let's rearrange our shapes, so the circle 
					is inscribed within our square.
					<br>
					<br>
					<img src="./experiments/inscribed.png" width="200" height="200" style="	display: block; margin-left: auto;margin-right: auto;">
					<br>
					<br>
					Maybe it will be easier to think of another way of representing the area of our 
					circle now. Well, we can easily figure out the area of the square, so why don't 
					we just multiply the area of the square by the percent of the square that the 
					circle occupies? 
					\begin{equation}
						A_{\small{\bigcirc}} = A_{\Box}(P_{\bigcirc in \Box})
					\end{equation}
					where $P_{\bigcirc in \Box}$ is the percent of the square's area which the circle occupies.
					Sounds reasonable, right? Well how will we figure out that percent? If you are thinking 
					about probability then you are on the right track! Say we were to just randomly toss a 
					pebble somewhere within the square. What would be the probability that it would land inside 
					the inscribed circle? The answer is the percent of the square's area that the circle occupies! 
					This is perfect! So we just need to throw an infinite amount of stones into the square to get 
					the exact percent!
					\begin{equation}
						P_{\bigcirc in \Box} = \frac{\text{pebbles in circle}}{n} \text{ for } n\to \infty
					\end{equation}
					where $n$ is the total number of pebbles thrown.
					<br>
					Okay, now that we know how to solve for the percent of the square's area that the 
					circle occupies, we can substitute equations 1), 2), and 4) into equation 3) and solve for $\large{\pi}$.
					\begin{equation*}
						\pi r^{2} =(4r^{2})(\frac{\text{pebbles in circle}}{n}) \text{ for } n\to \infty
					\end{equation*}
					\begin{equation*}
						\pi = 4 (\frac{\text{pebbles in circle}}{n}) \text{ for } n\to \infty
					\end{equation*}
					So as the number of stones thrown gets bigger and bigger, we can expect our estimate of $\large{\pi}$, 
					which we are calling $\phi$, to get better and better, although the rate of convergence relies 
					on probability so the experiment will run differently each time.
					<br>
					<br>
					If you haven't done so already, click the experiment screen above to begin. You will observe 
					the circle inscribed within the square slowly fill up with randomly placed dots with the actual 
					value of $\large{\pi}$ and the estimated value, $\phi$, below. To the right is a figure which shows the actual 
					value of $\large{\pi}$ as a yellow line and the different estimations generates for each iteration being 
					dynamically plotted. Typically the first two decimal digits take anywhere between 50,000 to 
					200,000 iterations to converge, so it requires a little patience. 
					]]>
					
		</Description> 
		<Footnotes>
			<![CDATA[
			$^{1}$Now, you may be wondering why we don't just model the coin toss to make it 
			predictable since the physics is all pretty well defined: the initial impulse 
			force, the torque and angular momentum of the coin, the orientation of the 
			surface on which it lands, et cetera. While this may be true, it would be an 
			awful amount of work and may prove impractical. So, in a sense, a coin toss is not 
			a true random event. Though by this logic there may be no true random events 
			since it is conceivable-- assuming that we are all causal determinists here-- 
			that every event can be determined by a theoretical set of causes. But we digress. 
			And, for practicality we will view the coin toss as a random event. 
			]]>
		</Footnotes>
	</demo>
</Demos>